Hello, I'm Joy, a poet of code,
مرحبا أُدعى (جوي)، أَنظُم الشعر على الحاسوب
on a mission to stop an unseen force that's rising,
في مهمة لردع قوة ناشئة غير مرئية،
a force that I called "the coded gaze,"
قوة أسميتها "النظرة المشفرَّة،"
my term for algorithmic bias.
مصطلح أطلقه عن تحيز الخوارزمية.
Algorithmic bias, like human bias, results in unfairness.
تحيز الخوارزمية مثل تحيز البشر يؤدي إلى الإجحاف.
However, algorithms, like viruses, can spread bias on a massive scale
برغم ذلك، الخوارزميات مثل الفيروسات يتفشى فيها التحيز على مستوى واسع
at a rapid pace.
بخطى سريعة.
Algorithmic bias can also lead to exclusionary experiences
تحيز الخوارزمية قد يُفضِي إلى وقوع حوادث إقصائية
and discriminatory practices.
و ممارسات تمييزية.
Let me show you what I mean.
دعوني أوضح ما أعنيه.
(Video) Joy Buolamwini: Hi, camera. I've got a face.
(فيديو): أهلا بالكاميرا. لدي وجه.
Can you see my face?
هل ترون وجهي؟
No-glasses face?
وجه بلا نظارات؟
You can see her face.
تستطيع رؤية وجهها.
What about my face?
ماذا عن وجهي؟
I've got a mask. Can you see my mask?
لدي قناع. هل ترى قناعي؟
Joy Buolamwini: So how did this happen?
إذن كيف حدث هذا؟
Why am I sitting in front of a computer
لمَ أجلس أمام حاسوب
in a white mask,
أضع قناعًا أبيض،
trying to be detected by a cheap webcam?
أحاول أن تكتشفني كاميرا ويب زهيدة؟
Well, when I'm not fighting the coded gaze
حسنا عندما لا أقاوم النظرة المشفرة
as a poet of code,
بصفتي شاعرة أستخدم التشفير،
I'm a graduate student at the MIT Media Lab,
أنا طالبة دراسات عليا في إم آي تي ميديا لاب،
and there I have the opportunity to work on all sorts of whimsical projects,
و هناك لدي الفرصة للعمل على جميع أنواع المشروعات الغريبة،
including the Aspire Mirror,
بما في ذلك ( أسباير ميرور)،
a project I did so I could project digital masks onto my reflection.
مشروع قمت به لأرسم أقنعة رقْمية على انعكاسي.
So in the morning, if I wanted to feel powerful,
لذا في الصباح إذا أردت الشعور بالقوة،
I could put on a lion.
أستطيع أن أضع قناع أسد.
If I wanted to be uplifted, I might have a quote.
إذا أردت أن أرفع معنوياتي، قد أحصل على اقتباس.
So I used generic facial recognition software
لذا استخدمت برمجة موسعة للتعرف على الوجه
to build the system,
لبناء النظام،
but found it was really hard to test it unless I wore a white mask.
لكني وجدت أنه من الصعب اختباره مالم أضع قناعًا.
Unfortunately, I've run into this issue before.
لسوء الحظ واجهتني هذه المسألة من قبل.
When I was an undergraduate at Georgia Tech studying computer science,
عندما كنت طالبة في جامعة جورجيا التقنية أدرس علوم الحاسب،
I used to work on social robots,
اعتدت العمل على الروبوتات الاجتماعية،
and one of my tasks was to get a robot to play peek-a-boo,
و إحدى مهامي كانت أن أجعل روبوت يلعب بيكابو (لعبة الاختفاء)،
a simple turn-taking game
لعبة بسيطة لتناوب الأدوار
where partners cover their face and then uncover it saying, "Peek-a-boo!"
حيث يغطي الشخص وجهه عن شريكه ثم يكشفه قائلا، "بيكابو!"
The problem is, peek-a-boo doesn't really work if I can't see you,
المشكلة أن هذه اللعبة لا تعمل حقيقةً إذا لم أستطع رؤيتك،
and my robot couldn't see me.
و روبوتي لا يستطيع رؤيتي.
But I borrowed my roommate's face to get the project done,
لكني استعنت بوجه زميلتي بالسكن لكي أنهي المشروع،
submitted the assignment,
وقدمت المَهًمّة،
and figured, you know what, somebody else will solve this problem.
ووجدت أن شخصا آخر قد حل هذه المشكلة.
Not too long after,
ليس بعد وقت طويل حينها،
I was in Hong Kong for an entrepreneurship competition.
كنت في هونغ كونغ لأجل مسابقة في ريادة الأعمال.
The organizers decided to take participants
قرر المنظمون أن يأخذوا المشاركين
on a tour of local start-ups.
في جولة للشركات الناشئة المحلية.
One of the start-ups had a social robot,
إحدى هذه الشركات كان لديها روبوت اجتماعي،
and they decided to do a demo.
و قرروا استخدام عرض توضيحي.
The demo worked on everybody until it got to me,
عمل العرض التوضيحي مع الجميع حتى جاء دوري،
and you can probably guess it.
ربما تستطيع تخيل الأمر.
It couldn't detect my face.
لم يتعرف على وجهي.
I asked the developers what was going on,
سألت المطورين عما يحدث،
and it turned out we had used the same generic facial recognition software.
واتضح أننا استخدمنا نفس البرمجة العامة للتعرف على الوجه.
Halfway around the world,
جبت نصف العالم،
I learned that algorithmic bias can travel as quickly
لأعلم أن تحيز الخوارزمية يستطيع الانتقال بسرعة
as it takes to download some files off of the internet.
قدر ما يأخذه الوقت لتحميل بعض الملفات من شبكة الانترنت.
So what's going on? Why isn't my face being detected?
إذن ما الذي يحدث؟ لم لا يتعرف على وجهي؟
Well, we have to look at how we give machines sight.
حسنا، علينا أن ننظر إلى كيفية تفعيل حاسة البصر عند الآلات.
Computer vision uses machine learning techniques
يستخدم البصر الحاسوبي تقنيات خاصة بتعلم الآلة
to do facial recognition.
للقيام بالتعرف على الوجه.
So how this works is, you create a training set with examples of faces.
إذن يتفعل هذا بإنشاء جهاز تدريب مزود بأمثلة للأوجه.
This is a face. This is a face. This is not a face.
هذا وجه. هذا وجه. هذا ليس بوجه.
And over time, you can teach a computer how to recognize other faces.
وبمرور الوقت، يتعلم الحاسوب كيف يتعرف على وجوه أخرى.
However, if the training sets aren't really that diverse,
برغم ذلك، إذا لم تكن أجهزة التدريب متنوعة،
any face that deviates too much from the established norm
ووجد وجه يختلف كثيرا عن النمط القائم
will be harder to detect,
سيكون أصعب في التعرف عليه،
which is what was happening to me.
الأمر الذي حدث معي.
But don't worry -- there's some good news.
لكن لا تقلقوا -- هناك أخبار جيدة.
Training sets don't just materialize out of nowhere.
أجهزة التدريب لا تحقق إنجازًا من لاشيء.
We actually can create them.
نستطيع بالفعل أن ننشئهم.
So there's an opportunity to create full-spectrum training sets
إذن هناك فرصة لإنتاج أجهزة تدريب تمسح الطيف الكامل
that reflect a richer portrait of humanity.
التي تعكس صورا تُثري الإنسانية أكثر.
Now you've seen in my examples
الآن قد رأيتم في أمثلتي
how social robots
كيف أن الروبوتات الاجتماعية
was how I found out about exclusion with algorithmic bias.
كشفت لي الإقصاء المنتهج في تحيز الخوارزمية.
But algorithmic bias can also lead to discriminatory practices.
لكن قد يؤدي تحيز الخوارزمية إلى الممارسات التمييزية أيضا.
Across the US,
عبر الولايات المتحدة،
police departments are starting to use facial recognition software
بدأت أقسام الشرطة في استخدام برمجة التعرف على الوجه
in their crime-fighting arsenal.
كسلاح لمكافحة الجريمة.
Georgetown Law published a report
نشرت كلية حقوق جورج تاون تقريراً
showing that one in two adults in the US -- that's 117 million people --
يظهر أن بالغاً من كل اثنين في الولايات المتحدة -- حوالى 117 مليون نسمة --
have their faces in facial recognition networks.
توجد بصمة وجهه في شبكات التعرف على الوجه.
Police departments can currently look at these networks unregulated,
تتمكن أقسام الشرطة حالياً من تفحص هذه الشبكات بطريقة غير منظمة،
using algorithms that have not been audited for accuracy.
باستخدام خوارزميات لم يراع فيها الدقة.
Yet we know facial recognition is not fail proof,
حتى الآن لم يثبَت فشل التعرف على الوجه،
and labeling faces consistently remains a challenge.
ويظل تصنيف الوجوه تحدياً مستمراً.
You might have seen this on Facebook.
قد تكون رأيت هذا في فيسبوك.
My friends and I laugh all the time when we see other people
أضحك كثيرا أنا وأصدقائي عندما نرى الآخرين
mislabeled in our photos.
غير مصنَّفين في صورنا.
But misidentifying a suspected criminal is no laughing matter,
لكن عدم تحديد مجرماً مشتبهاً به ليس أمراً مضحكاً،
nor is breaching civil liberties.
ولا انتهاكاً للحريات المدنية.
Machine learning is being used for facial recognition,
التعلم الآلي يستخدم في التعرف على الوجه،
but it's also extending beyond the realm of computer vision.
لكنه أيضا يتجاوز حدود رؤية الحاسوب.
In her book, "Weapons of Math Destruction,"
في كتابها، "أسلحة الدمار الحسابيّ،"
data scientist Cathy O'Neil talks about the rising new WMDs --
تحدثت عالمة البيانات (كاثي أونيل) عن هذه الأسلحة الصاعدة --
widespread, mysterious and destructive algorithms
الخوارزميات الرائجة والغامضة والمدمرة
that are increasingly being used to make decisions
التي تُستخدم بتزايد في اتخاذ القرارات
that impact more aspects of our lives.
التي تؤثر على نواحي أكثر في حياتنا.
So who gets hired or fired?
إذن من يُوظَّف أو يُطرَد؟
Do you get that loan? Do you get insurance?
هل تحصل على ذاك القرض؟ هل تحصل على التأمين؟
Are you admitted into the college you wanted to get into?
هل قُبلت بالكلية التي أردتها؟
Do you and I pay the same price for the same product
هل يدفع الجميع نفس السعرعن نفس المنتج
purchased on the same platform?
الذي اشتُرِي من نفس المنصة؟
Law enforcement is also starting to use machine learning
بدأ مسؤولو تطبيق القانون في استخدام التعلم الآلي
for predictive policing.
لغرض الفاعلية في حفظ الأمن.
Some judges use machine-generated risk scores to determine
بعض القضاة يحددون درجات الخطر باستخدام الآلة لمعرفة
how long an individual is going to spend in prison.
طول المدة التي سيقضيها الفرد في السجن.
So we really have to think about these decisions.
بالتالي علينا أن نفكر مليًّا في هذه القرارات.
Are they fair?
هل هي عادلة؟
And we've seen that algorithmic bias
و لقد رأينا أن تحيز الخوارزمية
doesn't necessarily always lead to fair outcomes.
لا يؤدي بالضرورة إلى نتائج عادلة دائما.
So what can we do about it?
ما الذي يمكن فعله حيال هذا؟
Well, we can start thinking about how we create more inclusive code
حسنا، نستطيع البدء في إنتاج تشفير أكثر تضميناً
and employ inclusive coding practices.
و نوظف ممارسات تشفير شاملة.
It really starts with people.
إن الناس هم من يبادروا.
So who codes matters.
لذا من يقوم بالتشفير له أهمية.
Are we creating full-spectrum teams with diverse individuals
هل ننتج مجموعات للطيف الكامل بها أفراد متنوعين
who can check each other's blind spots?
من يستطيع فحص النقاط غير المرئية لبعضهم البعض؟
On the technical side, how we code matters.
على الصعيد الفني، يوجد أهمية لكيفية التشفير.
Are we factoring in fairness as we're developing systems?
هل نصنّع بعَدْل بينما نطور النظام؟
And finally, why we code matters.
و في النهاية لمً نقوم بالتشفير.
We've used tools of computational creation to unlock immense wealth.
لقد استخدمنا أدوات للإعداد الحاسوبي لكشف الثروة الهائلة.
We now have the opportunity to unlock even greater equality
لدينا الآن الفرصة لكشف جودة أكبر
if we make social change a priority
إذا جعلنا من التغير الاجتماعي أولوية
and not an afterthought.
و ليس كتفكير مؤجَّل.
And so these are the three tenets that will make up the "incoding" movement.
و هذه الركائز الثلاثة التي ستشعل حركة التشفير.
Who codes matters,
من يشفر له أهمية،
how we code matters
كيف نشفر مهم
and why we code matters.
ولمِاذا نشفر مهم أيضا.
So to go towards incoding, we can start thinking about
إذن لنتحول للتشفير نستطيع البدء بالتفكير في
building platforms that can identify bias
بناء منصات تستطيع تحديد التحيز
by collecting people's experiences like the ones I shared,
بواسطة جمع خبرات الناس مثل تلك التي شاركتها،
but also auditing existing software.
أيضا التدقيق في البرمجة الحالية.
We can also start to create more inclusive training sets.
نستطيع أيضا إنشاء أدوات تدريب شاملة أكثر.
Imagine a "Selfies for Inclusion" campaign
تخيل حملة بعنوان" سيلفي للتضمين"
where you and I can help developers test and create
حيث نستطيع جميعا مساعدة المطورين لاختبار و إنتاج
more inclusive training sets.
أجهزة تدريب أكثر شمولية.
And we can also start thinking more conscientiously
و نستطيع التفكير بطريقة أكثر وعياً
about the social impact of the technology that we're developing.
تجاه التأثير الاجتماعي للتكنولوجيا التي نطورها.
To get the incoding movement started,
لكي نفعل حركة التشفير،
I've launched the Algorithmic Justice League,
أطللقت رابطة باسم العدالة الخوارزمية،
where anyone who cares about fairness can help fight the coded gaze.
حيث يستطيع كل من يهتم بالعدل أن يكافح ضد النظرة المشفرة.
On codedgaze.com, you can report bias,
يمكنكم التبليغ عن التحيز على موقع codedgaze.com
request audits, become a tester
وتطالب بالتدقيق وتصبح مُختبِراً
and join the ongoing conversation,
و تنضم للمحادثة الدائرة،
#codedgaze.
على وسْم #codegaze.
So I invite you to join me
لذا أدعوكم للانضمام إليّ
in creating a world where technology works for all of us,
في إيجاد عالم حيث تعمل فيه التكنولوجيا من أجل الجميع،
not just some of us,
ليس البعض منا فحسب،
a world where we value inclusion and center social change.
عالم حيث نقدّر التضمين و نركز على التغير الاجتماعي.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But I have one question:
لكن لدي سؤال واحد:
Will you join me in the fight?
هل ستنضمون إلي في الكفاح؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)